Hello.
I'm Mia.
Welcome to Oxford Online English!
In this lesson, you can learn about the Cambridge
FCE speaking exam, part three.
Do you know what to expect in this part of
the exam or what the examiners are looking
for?
In this lesson, you can see what will happen
in part three of the speaking test and how
to improve your score.
Part One: what to expect in part three of
the FCE speaking exam.
So what happens in part three of your FCE
speaking test?
Part three of the exam is divided into two
parts.
In the first part, you and your partner will
be given five written prompts and asked a
question.
You'll have about two minutes to discuss the
Look at a sample question.
In this example, the question is, "Why might
people choose to wear these different clothes?"
All of these questions have a similar format.
The question is in the centre with five prompts
around the sides.
After you finish talking to your partner,
the examiner will ask you and your partner
a question about the subject you've just discussed.
For example, "Which of these clothes would
people feel more comfortable wearing?"
Or, "Which clothes would be best to wear for
a job interview?"
You'll have about one minute to discuss this
question with your partner.
So what do you need to do to improve your
score in part three of the FCE speaking test?
Part Two: interactive communication and improving
your score.
Like the other parts of the FCE speaking exam,
you are given scores for grammar, vocabulary,
discourse management--whether you can speak
fluently and coherently--and pronunciation.
In part three, you also get a score for interactive
communication.
This means that your score depends partly
on how you communicate with your partner.
This means it's important to work with your
partner and speak together.
In our videos in part one and part two of
the FCE speaking exam, we've discussed how
to improve your grammar, vocabulary, and discourse
management scores.
Now, let's focus on your interactive communication
score and what you can do to improve it.
So what are the examiners looking for?
The examiners want to know: can you begin
a conversation?
Are you able to listen and respond to your
partner in an appropriate way?
Can you keep the conversation going?
Can you ask your partner questions?
Can you take turns with your partner, speaking
when it's your turn but also giving your partner
the chance to speak?
Here are some good ways to improve your interactive
communication score.
Take short turns.
It's a good idea to take short turns when
speaking with your partner.
This way, the conversation moves quickly,
and you can discuss more of the written prompts.
First, don't speak for too long.
Express an idea, and then ask your partner
a question.
When your partner speaks, comment on what
they say and ask new questions.
This way, you will sound natural and engaged.
This will improve your score on the exam.
Use body language.
Body language is an important part of expressing
yourself.
Turn towards your partner, and make eye contact.
Remember, you're talking to your partner,
not to the examiners.
This will also make the conversation more
natural and help you to relax.
Make sure you look interested in what your
partner is saying.
Even if they're the most boring person you've
ever met, you need to pay attention to what
they're saying so that you can respond appropriately.
Express your opinions.
It's good to agree and disagree with your
partner.
This will help you to express your opinions
and have a more natural conversation.
Make sure you disagree politely so that you
don't offend your partner.
For example, "I disagree that a dress and
high heels would be a good choice for going
out with friends.
I think that jeans and a jumper could be a
lot more comfortable, and you could make them
look stylish, too."
While this answer expresses disagreement,
it's also polite and helps to move the conversation
forward.
Ask questions.
It's always a good idea to ask your partner
questions.
They could be simple or complex.
A good time to ask a question is after you
disagree with your partner.
Look at the previous example again, "I think
that jeans and a jumper could be a lot more
comfortable, and you could make them look
stylish, too.
What about shorts and a T-shirt?
When do you think people might wear them?"
Asking your partner a question after you disagree
with them moves the conversation forward and
stops any possible arguments.
It will also give you a higher score in your
interactive communication mark.
Part Three: useful phrases and expressions.
Next, let's look at some useful phrases and
expressions that you can use in this part
of the FCE speaking test.
Firstly, it's a good idea to ask your partner
if they would like to start the conversation.
You are showing the examiner that you can
begin the conversation, and at the same time,
giving yourself more time to think about the
task.
You could say, "Would you like to begin?"
Or if you're more confident and want to dive
straight in, "Shall I start?"
Now that you've begun, let's look at some
phrases you can use to agree with your partner.
You could simply say, "I agree with you,"
or, "That's a good idea."
However, these phrases are quite basic and
can be repetitive.
Try using some more interesting phrases, such
as, "I see your point," or, "You make some
great points."
Or if you really agree with them, "I couldn't
agree with you more."
"You're absolutely right."
So what do you do if you disagree?
If you disagree, it's a good idea to use a
polite phrase and keep the conversation moving.
This will make you sound more fluid and avoid
getting into arguments.
You could tell your partner, "I'm not sure
I agree," or, "I get your point, but..." or,
"That's one way of looking at it.
On the other hand..."
You can see that all these phrases allow you
to continue and explain your point, helping
you to keep the conversation moving.
Part Four: how to deal with difficult partners.
Okay.
But what if your partner isn't letting you
speak?
What if your partner isn't taking part in
the conversation at all?
What can you do?
Don't worry.
This is unlikely to happen, but knowing what
to do in this situation will help you feel
more confident in your speaking test.
Firstly, imagine that you're in the exam and
your partner won't stop talking about the
same point.
What do you do?
You interrupt them.
Be polite about it, and say something like,
"That's an interesting point, but what about
this idea?" or, "Okay, let's discuss this
point next," or, "Shall we move on to this
point now?"
These phrases will show that you need to continue
with the task and will also give you a higher
score because you are interacting with them
and moving the conversation forward.
Now, imagine that you're in the exam with
the same partner, only this time they don't
want to talk.
They are very shy and quiet and don't speak
much to you.
What would you do in this situation?
In this situation, it's a good idea to ask
your partner questions.
Of course, you should ask your partner questions
anyway.
But if they really don't speak much, ask them
more.
You could simply ask, "What do you think?"
"Which do you prefer?"
"Do you think it's a good idea to...?"
Or you could ask more specific questions.
For example, "What's your opinion on these
clothes?" or, "What are your views on this
question?"
Now that you've seen some useful phrases,
we'll look at some sample questions and answers.
Part Five: sample questions and answers.
Now, let's start putting all of that information
together and looking at how to make great
answers.
Have a look at this question.
The question is, "Why are these inventions
important in everyday life?"
Your partner begins and says, "In my opinion,
computers and mobile phones are the most important
inventions because we use them for everything
in our day-to-day lives."
Now, look at this sample answer, "I think
that all of these inventions are very important
in modern society, and we use most of them
every day.
However, I don't think it's as important to
have separate mobile phones and computers
as nowadays we have smart phones which are
like small computers."
This answer is grammatically good and uses
a variety of vocabulary.
However, there's a big problem here.
Can you see the problem?
The problem is that there isn't any interaction
with the partner.
Your partner has just made an interesting
statement, which you haven't responded to
at all.
But don't worry.
This is easily fixed.
Have a look again.
"That's a good point.
However, I don't think it's as important to
have separate mobile phones and computers
as nowadays we have smart phones which are
like small computers.
What's your opinion on this?"
This is much better.
Remember, you need to take short turns at
speaking with plenty of interaction with your
partner.
Don't talk for too long.
Now, imagine that you have discussed all of
the prompts with your partner.
The examiner asks you, "Which of these inventions
do you think is the least important?"
You have one minute to discuss this new question
and reach some sort of conclusion.
Take a look at this answer, "In my opinion,
the dishwasher is the least important because
it's not necessary to use one to clean your
plates and things.
What do you think?"
This is okay, but it's a common problem to
answer the question too early.
Remember, you have about a minute for the
question.
Now, have a look at this answer, "From what
you said earlier, I liked your idea that computers
are less necessary these days because everyone
has smart phones and tablets.
Do you think that this means that computers
aren't important any more?"
This is a good answer because you're discussing
the question in depth with your partner.
You're asking questions and referring back
to your partner's past answers.
This shows the examiner that you can have
a complex conversation.
This would get you a higher score in your
interactive communication.
Now that we've looked at what you can expect
in part three of your FCE speaking exam and
some useful tips and phrases, I hope you're
feeling confident and ready for your test.
Good luck!
That's the end of the lesson.
Thanks very much for watching.
I hope you found it useful.
You can see more of our free lessons on our
website, oxfordonlineenglish.com.
See you next time!