Hi.
My name is Rheedan.
Welcome to Oxford Online English!
Today, we're going to learn some important
words and phrases, so that you can order your
next cup of coffee in English.
Do you often go for coffee?
Do you know how to order different types of
coffee in English?
You'll learn how in this lesson.
Let's first look at some words you'll need
to know when ordering your morning cup.
At a coffee shop, drinks are usually made
from espresso.
An espresso is a small amount of very strong
coffee.
This small amount is called a shot.
This espresso is then drunk on its own or
mixed in different ways to make the different
coffee drinks.
Here are some of the most common.
Americano: espresso with hot water.
Cappuccino: espresso and steamed milk, with
foamed milk or cream on top.
Latte: espresso with lots of steamed milk.
Mocha: espresso, hot chocolate, and steamed
milk, sometimes with cream on top.
Which of these types of coffee have you tried?
Personally, I like lattes.
You can also have your coffee with different
kinds of milk, like low-fat, fat-free, or
soy.
If you want coffee without milk, ask for a
black coffee.
Some people also like to have things added
to their coffee, like caramel, chocolate,
or vanilla syrup, or cream.
You can even have an extra shot of espresso
added.
You also have a choice of sizes.
You can get a small, medium, large, or extra
large.
Many coffee shops have their own names for
these sizes, but you don't need to know or
use them.
Just using these sizes will work.
How to order coffee: when giving your order,
you usually say the size first, then the type
of coffee, and then the type of milk or extras.
For example, "Small cappuccino with caramel
syrup" or, "Medium mocha without cream."
If you want a cold drink, you add the word
"iced" before the type of coffee.
For example, "Large iced latte with low-fat
milk" or, "Medium iced Americano."
Placing your order: a barista is someone who
makes coffee.
They will usually take your order.
There are a few things they can say, such
as, "May I take your order?"
"What would you like?"
"What can I get you?"
"What will you have?"
You can answer in a few different ways.
You can say, "I would like . . ." "I'll have
. . ." or, "Can I get . . .?" Then you give
your order: "I'll have an Americano with vanilla
syrup."
Or, "Can I get a latte with extra cream, please?"
What's this order missing?
If you make an order like this, the first
question you will be asked is, "What size
would you like?"
"What size will that be?"
Another question you might hear when making
your order is, "Is that for here or to take
away?"
You can answer, "For here," "To take away,"
or, "To go."
You can also add this information to your
order.
What does that look like?
When you order, you can just say, "I'd like
a small mocha without cream to go," or, "I'll
have a medium iced latte with vanilla syrup,
for here."
After you order, the barista might say, "Will
that be all?"
"Is that everything?"
"Would you like anything else?"
Finally, the barista will tell you the total
cost.
"Your total is . . ." "That comes to . . ." "That
will be . . ." When handing over your money,
you can say, "Here you are," or, "Here you
go."
Once you've paid, you'll both say, "Thank
you," and that's it.
You've just successfully ordered coffee in
English.
Let's look at a sample dialogue.
"Hi.
What'll you have?"
"I"d like a large latte."
"Will that be all?"
"Yes, thank you."
"Is that for here?
Or to go?"
"To go."
"Your total comes to $4."
"Here you go."
"Thanks very much."
"Thank you.
Have a nice day."
Let's look at one more.
"Hi.
What can I get you?"
"I'll have a small mocha with cream and a
small cappuccino, for here."
"Would you like anything else?"
"Yes, I'd also like an espresso."
"Is that everything?"
"Yes."
"That will be six pounds."
"Here you go."
"Here's your change."
"Thanks."
"Thanks very much."
There you go.
Now you'll be able to order your next cup
of coffee in English.
Want more practice?
Look at the full lesson on our website, oxfordonlineenglish.com.
That's it from me.
I hope the lesson helped.
See you next time!