Hi, I'm Mike. Welcome to Oxford Online English.
In this lesson, you can learn about the modal
verb 'would' in English. Would you like to
learn more about 'would' and what it means?
If I asked you to tell me all the meanings
and uses of 'would' right now would you be
able to? Like all modal verbs, 'would' can
have many different meanings. These different
meanings aren't connected to each other, which
can make it difficult to work out what 'would'
means in different sentences or situations.
In this class, you'll see all the uses of
'would' and meanings. Let's start with the
most important use of 'would'.
Imagine your friend asks you:
What would you do if you were attacked by
a shark?
Why does your friend use would in this question?
And how should you answer?
Probably, your answer would also include would.
Maybe something like:
I’d probably try to hit it on the nose,
or poke it in the eye, or something like that.
Maybe I’d just try to swim away.
So, any ideas? Why do we use would here?
It’s because getting attacked by a shark
is very unlikely. We use would when we talk
about things which are either very unlikely,
or totally impossible.
For example:
What would you do if you could read people’s
thoughts?
Reading people’s thoughts is impossible,
so we use would. It’s a question about an
imaginary situation.
I would help you if I could.
I can’t help you, so I use would to show
that it’s impossible. This is like saying,
“I can’t help you.”
She would be here, but he has too much work
at the moment.
She’s not here, although she would be if
she didn’t have so much work.
In all of these cases, when you use would,
you’re talking about a situation which isn’t
true, and which you think will never happen.
That’s what it means when you use would
like this. You’re saying, “I think this
thing will never happen.”
If I won the lottery, I would…
You say would because you don’t think you’ll
ever win the lottery.
You can use would have plus a past participle
to talk about the past in the same way. For
example:
What would you have said if she’d seen you?
She didn’t see you, so you didn’t say
anything to her. I’m asking you a question
about an imaginary situation. I’m saying,
“Imagine a different version of the past,
where she did see you…”
I wouldn’t have come if I’d known it was
going to go on so late.
I didn’t know it was going to go on so late,
so I did come, but now I regret it! Imagine
you’re at an event and you have to get up
early tomorrow. The event goes on much later
than you expected, so you say this.
He wouldn’t have been much help, anyway.
He wasn’t there, so he couldn’t help,
but even if he had been there, he wouldn’t
have been able to help us.
This is the most common way to use would,
and probably the most complicated. However,
would has many other uses.
Let’s look!
If you want to ask someone to do something
for you, using would in your request can make
it sound more polite.
For example:
Can you tell me the time?
Will you get me a sandwich?
I want something to eat.
All of these requests are quite informal.
That can be fine, depending on the situation,
but sometimes you want to be a bit more formal,
so that you sound polite.
Would can be useful here. Look at the sentences.
Can you see how to use would?
Okay, let’s check your ideas:
Would you mind telling me the time?
Would you get me a sandwich?
I’d like something to eat.
Using would you mind + -ing is a very polite
way to make a request.
You can also use would in place of will in
a request. This makes it a little more formal
and polite.
Finally, using would like instead of want
is better, unless you’re in a very informal
situation.
To be clear, these aren’t the only ways
to use would. There are other possible answers.
For example, you could say:
Tell me the time, would you?
Would you mind getting me a sandwich?
These are possible, but the first answers
I gave you are the most obvious.
Also, let’s get something clear: there’s
no connection between these different uses
of would.
If you use would to make a polite request,
like you’re doing here, there’s no connection
with the idea of imaginary or unreal situations
that you saw in part one.
Okay, let’s move on and look at another
way to use would.
Imagine you have a friend who’s always late
for everything. You’re meeting your friend
tomorrow, and you’re really annoyed that
you always have to wait. You tell your friend
to be on time, and she replies:
I’ll be on time, I promise! I’ll get an
earlier bus, which will get to the centre
by 3.00.
Now, imagine that it’s a few days later,
and you want to tell me what your friend said
to you. How would you do it?
You would say something like:
My friend promised she’d be on time. She
said she’d get an earlier bus, which she
said would arrive by 3.00. Of course, when
she turned up it was nearly 4.00!
Do you see what’s happening here?
Every time your friend says will, you say
would when you’re talking about what your
friend said.
English learners often say something like,
“Would is the past tense of will.” That’s
true sometimes, but not generally.
For example, for the uses of would you saw
in parts one and two, it’s not helpful or
accurate to say that would is the past tense
of will.
However, in reported speech, it’s a good
way to think about it.
There’s one more case where would has a
past meaning connected to will.
Do you know what I’m talking about?
Both will and would can have the meaning of
refusing to do something. For example:
I’ll ask him, but he won’t help me. He’ll
refuse to help me (in the future).
I asked him, but he wouldn’t help me. He
refused to help me (in the past).
In this case, you can use would as the past
version of will.
You can use this to talk about people:
They wouldn’t give me my money back, even
though I had the receipt.
They refused to give me my money back.
You can also use it to talk about things:
My car wouldn’t start this morning.
My car ‘refused’ to start. Okay, cars
can’t literally refuse to start, but we
often talk about machines, computers and things
like that in this way.
Here’s a similar example:
When he tried to show me, the file wouldn’t
open.
So here and in part three—reported speech—the
meanings of will and would are connected.
When you’re thinking about how to use will
and would, it’s important to remember that
sometimes the meanings are connected, and
sometimes they’re completely different.
We’ll come back to this point at the end
of the lesson.
There’s one more way to use would that we
need to look at:
You can use would to talk about things you
did in the past, but don’t do now.
For example:
My mum would walk us to school when we were
little.
When I was training for the marathon, I would
go running for two hours every day after work.
It was exhausting!
Would is similar to used to here, but it’s
not exactly the same.
When you use would like this, you can only
talk about repeated actions in the past. You
can’t talk about states and situations,
like you can with used to.
So, you can’t say:
I would live in a small flat with my friends
when I was a student.
That’s not correct, because live is a state,
not an action.
However, this sentence is okay:
I would go out with my friends most evenings
when I was a student.
This is fine, because go out is an action.
So, now you’ve seen all the different ways
you can use would in English.
Let’s review what you’ve learned today.
Would has five common uses in English. It
can be used:
To talk about imaginary or unreal situations.
To make polite requests.
In reported speech, as the past version of
will.
To mean ‘refused to’.
To talk about repeated actions in the past.
When you’re learning about how to use would,
one of the most important things to get clear
in your head is the relationship between will
and would.
Sometimes will and would are connected: if
you’re using reported speech, or using would
to mean ‘refused to’, then would behaves
like a past version of will.
However, in the other uses of would, there
is no connection between will and would. In
fact, in the most common use of would—talking
about imaginary or unreal situations—will
and would have almost opposite meanings.
For example, if someone says, “I’ll help
you,” with will, you can expect them to
help you, in reality.
If someone says, “I would help you,” with
would, then you shouldn’t expect them to
help you. Will and would have completely different
meanings here.
It’s also good to remember that the different
uses of would aren’t connected to each other
at all. The meaning of would depends completely
on the sentence and the situation.
Finally, would can refer to different times
depending on how you’re using would. For
example:
I would come tomorrow, but I’ve already
made other plans.
Would you pass me that blue bag?
I asked them to change my ticket, but they
wouldn’t do anything.
These three sentences are about the future,
the present and the past, respectively.
So you can’t say what time would refers
to by itself. It can refer to any time depending
on the meaning and the context.
Most importantly, would doesn’t necessarily
have a past meaning. Sometimes it does, but
it can also refer to the present or
the future.
Thanks a lot for watching!