Hi, I'm Mike.
Welcome to Oxford Online English.
In this lesson, you can learn how to write
an email in English.
Do you need to write emails at work?
Are you worried that your emails aren’t
clear, or that you make mistakes in English?
In this lesson, you can see a how to write
clear, natural-sounding emails easily and
quickly.
We’ll show you how to write an email in
English from beginning to end, in simple,
clear steps that you can follow right now!
Let’s start at the beginning.
With emails, you can start like a letter.
For example:
Dear Lina,
Dear Sir/Madam,
Dear Mr Hill,
However, emails are generally much less formal
than letters.
Use a greeting with 'dear' only if you’re
writing something formal.
So, what else can you use?
Many emails start with hello, or hi plus the
person’s name.
For example,
Hello,
Hi Ryan,
In many business emails, you’ll follow the
greeting with something like:
I hope you’re well.
or
How are you?
In business emails, these are simply polite
phrases, and they don’t generally need an
answer.
For more informal emails, you can start with
just the word hi or hey, plus a comma:
You can also just write the person’s name
plus a comma.
This is a more professional style, even though
it’s more informal.
It’s best with people you already know.
For a very informal email, you might not need
a greeting at all.
This is also true if you’re sending several
emails to the same person in a short time:
you don’t need to write a greeting every
time.
Let’s review quickly:
For very formal emails, use a greeting with
dear plus a name, like a letter.
For most everyday emails, use either hello
or hi plus a name.
For less formal emails, use hi or hey without
a name, or don’t use a greeting at all.
Okay, but what next?
After your greeting, you should explain why
you’re writing.
Make this as short as possible.
If you’re writing to someone who receives
hundreds of emails every day, you need to
make your purpose clear quickly.
Someone who’s very busy won’t spend a
lot of time trying to work out what you’re
trying to say!
How can you do this?
Start with a simple phrase, like:
I’m writing regarding…
I wanted to follow up on…
I would like to ask about…
These phrases are slightly more formal.
Let’s see how you could use them:
I’m writing regarding the issues we’ve
been having with our database system.
I wanted to follow up on our meeting last
week and confirm our plans for this month.
I would like to ask about the new budget and
whether this will affect our department.
In a more informal email, you wouldn’t use
a phrase like this.
You might ask a more direct question or make
a direct statement, like this:
Do you know when the database issues will
be fixed?
Let’s confirm our plans for this month.
How will the new budget affect our department?
If you’re writing because you want to find
a solution to a problem, here are some useful
phrases:
I’m concerned about… or
I need to bring something to your attention.
Again, these are more formal phrases.
Let’s see how you can use them:
I’m concerned about the number of sick days
staff have been taking recently.
I need to bring something to your attention:
using outdated software puts us at risk of
malware infections and data loss.
Now it’s your turn.
Imagine that you’re writing an email to
your manager, colleague, or client.
You need to write an appropriate greeting,
then write one or two sentences to explain
why you’re writing.
Pause the video and do it now!
Start again when you’ve finished.
Ready?
Let’s move on.
After you introduce why you’re writing,
you need to add more details and supporting information,
so that your reader understands the situation
you’re describing.
Put this information in a new paragraph.
This will make your email clear and easy to
follow.
First, ask yourself what the person you’re
writing to needs to know.
With emails, less is more.
No one wants to read a very long email, and
it’s hard to make yourself clear if you
write too much.
So, try to limit yourself to two to three
sentences.
Put your most important point first.
Let’s look at some examples:
I’m writing regarding the issues we’ve
been having with our database
Both clients and staff have been experiencing
severe problems for several days now.
We are unable to update records or access
information on customer interactions.
This is costing us large amounts of money,
both in time spent trying to fix the problem,
and in lost sales.
Here’s one more:
I’m concerned about the number of sick days
staff have been taking recently.
Staff in the IT department have taken a total
of 44 sick days so far this month, compared
to a total of 23 for last month, and just
18 for the previous month.
This is affecting productivity, and also placing
a lot of stress on the employees who do come
to work.
In both cases, you’re writing to describe
a problem.
Your first sentence introduces the problem,
and then your next paragraph gives more details.
You can see that in both examples, we use
just two sentences, but you can include a
lot of useful information in two sentences.
If you have more than one point to make in
your email, you can repeat this pattern: first
put a short sentence to introduce your point,
then add a paragraph with two to three sentences
to add details.
You can move from one point to another using
a phrase like:
There’s one more thing I’d like to discuss
with you.
Regarding…
I’d also like to ask you about…
Use one of these phrases to change the topic,
and then introduce your next point.
For example:
There’s one more thing I’d like to discuss
with you.
It seems like the number of customer complaints
has been increasing for three months…
Now, you can practice.
Take the email you started before.
Add a new paragraph, which should be two to
three sentences long.
Add details to the point you introduced before.
Pause the video and do it now.
If you want extra practice, add another topic
to your email, using one of the linking phrases
you just saw.
After you explain all the points you want
to make, what should you do next?
When you write an email, you should make it
clear what you expect from the person you’re
sending it to.
Even if you’re writing just to give the
other person some information, it’s a good
idea to make that clear.
Put your call to action in a new paragraph.
Again, putting each thing in its own paragraph
makes your email structured and easy to follow.
So, what can you write here?
First, let’s consider situations where you
need the other person to do something urgently.
You could say:
Please … by tomorrow at the latest.
As a matter of urgency, you need to…
For example:
Please arrange a meeting of all department
heads by tomorrow at the latest.
As a matter of urgency, you need to contact
all the clients who may have been affected
by this data breach.
If your request is less urgent, you could
use phrases such as:
Could you please…?
I would like you to…
For example:
Could you please talk to Matt in the HR department
and clarify our options on this?
I would like you to design a poster to inform
staff about the new policies.
With calls to action, you should think about
your relationship with the person you’re
writing to.
For example, saying something like, you need
to… or I would like you to… is relatively
direct.
That’s fine if you’re a manager writing
to one of your team, but it might sound inappropriate
if you write that to your manager.
This also depends on the corporate culture
where you work.
Generally, if you aren’t sure, it’s better
to be less direct.
For example:
I suggest that you contact all clients who
may have been affected by the data breach.
Can I ask you to design a poster to inform
staff about the new policies?
But, be careful!
Don’t be so indirect that the other person
doesn’t understand what you need.
If you don’t need a response from the other
person, say something like:
This is just to keep you updated.
This doesn’t require any immediate response,
but please keep an eye on the situation.
Now, it’s your turn!
Pause the video and add a call to action to
the end of your email.
Think about who you’re writing to, and make
your call-to-action appropriately direct or
indirect.
So, now you’re nearly finished.
What’s left?
Finish your email with a sign-off and your
name.
You can use a lot of the same sign-offs you
can use in a paper letter, such as:
Regards,
Best Wishes,
Kind Regards,
Like with greetings, you wouldn’t generally
use very formal sign-offs like Yours Sincerely
in an email.
You might see it sometimes, but only in very
formal emails.
Don’t forget to write each word of your
sign-off with a capital letter, and put a
comma at the end.
The sign-offs you’ve just seen are neutral
and can be used in almost any situation.
If you’re writing something more informal,
you might use a sign-off like:
Cheers,
Take care,
In this case, you wouldn’t capitalise each
word, which is why care in take care has a
small ‘c’.
Like with greetings, you might not need a
sign-off at all in an informal email.
Just write your name at the bottom, or don’t
write anything at all!
After you put your sign-off, add your name,
and you’ve finished!
For example,
Regards,
Vijay
Cheers,
Katya
Now you know how to write a clear, effective
email in English.
Let’s put everything you’ve learned together.
To write an effective email in English, you
need to:
1. Use an appropriate greeting.
2. Introduce your topic in a single sentence.
3. Add details to your topic in a short paragraph.
4. Add a call-to-action to explain what you need
the other person to do.
5. Use an appropriate signoff.
Let’s do a longer example together:
Dear Lina,
I need to bring something to your attention:
many staff are using very weak passwords on
their laptops and for database access.
Our work depends on keeping our clients’
personal financial information safe.
If we lose our clients’ trust on this issue,
it will not be easy to recover.
I trust that you can see that it is better
to take action now, rather than after something
goes wrong.
I suggest we make a rule that passwords must
be a specific length, and that staff must
change their passwords at least once a month.
Please let me know what you think about this.
Regards,
Vijay
What do you think: could you write an email
like this?
Try it!
Use words and phrases from the lesson.
Remember to organise your email into paragraphs,
like we showed you.
This will make it easier to keep your ideas
structured and clear.
For more free English lessons check out our website:
Oxford Online English dot com
Thanks for watching! See you next time!