Hi, I’m Martin. Welcome to Oxford Online
English! In this lesson, you can learn about
countable and uncountable nouns in English.
What’s the difference between paper and
a paper? Why do we say trousers are… but
news is…? Why can’t you say, Can you give
me an advice?
You’ll learn the answers to all these questions
in this lesson.
Where shall we start?
Some nouns are countable. You can count them.
For example, pens are countable. You can count
them.
One pen, two pens, three pens, and so on.
Some nouns are uncountable. You can’t count
them. For example, water is uncountable.
One water, two waters…? No, that doesn’t
work. You can’t count water.
Do you know any other uncountable nouns?
You’ll see more examples in the next section,
but here are three: money, rice and knowledge
are all uncountable nouns.
Countable and uncountable nouns behave differently.
They follow different rules.
First, uncountable nouns can’t be plural.
That means you can’t say moneys, rices or
knowledges. These forms don’t exist.
Secondly, you need to use a singular verb
with uncountable nouns. For example:
This rice doesn’t taste right.
Your money is on the table.
His knowledge of this subject has improved
significantly.
Next, you can’t use a or an with an uncountable
noun. You can’t say a rice, a money or a
knowledge. However, you can use some or any.
For example:
Is there any rice left?
You’ll need some money for the bus.
Finally, we use different words to talk about
quantities with countable and uncountable
nouns.
With countable nouns, we use many to talk
about large quantities, and few to talk about
small quantities.
With uncountable nouns, we use much and little.
You can use a lot of or lots of with both
countable and uncountable nouns.
For example:
There isn’t much rice left, but There aren’t
many potatoes left.
There’s a little money in my pocket, but
There are a few coins in that small box.
Okay, so now you know the basics about uncountable
nouns and how to use them.
Next, an important question:
Many uncountable nouns are words for food
and drink, such as pasta, meat, fruit, coffee,
beer or milk.
Be careful, because fruit is uncountable,
but vegetables are countable.
Many collective nouns are uncountable.
Collective nouns are nouns which describe
a group of objects all together. For example,
furniture, equipment, luggage or traffic.
Finally, abstract nouns are often uncountable.
For example: knowledge, information, advice
or progress.
Okay, I have a challenge for you.
You have three groups of nouns here: food
& drink, collective nouns, and abstract nouns.
I want you to pause the video and find one
more uncountable noun to add to each group.
That means you need to find one uncountable
food or drink noun, one uncountable collective
noun, and one uncountable abstract noun. Write
down your answers.
Why are you still here? Pause the video and
find your answers!
Okay, finished?
But, there’s a problem.
There are many possible answers you could
have here. How can you check?
Easy: find a dictionary. You can use an online
dictionary such as Longman, or a paper dictionary
if you’re feeling a bit old school.
Look up the words you wrote down. In the dictionary,
it should tell you if they’re countable
or uncountable.
Some dictionaries do this by adding a ‘u’
for uncountable or a ‘c’ for countable
after the noun. Different dictionaries have
different styles.
So now you can check your answers. Were you
correct?
Now, things get more complicated.
Why?
If nouns could only be countable or uncountable,
this topic would be very simple.
However, many nouns can be both countable
and uncountable, with different meanings.
For example, paper can be countable or uncountable.
Do you know the difference? What’s the difference
between paper and a paper?
Paper is the material: what you write on.
A paper is another way to say a newspaper
Let’s look at some more examples like this.
Think about it: what’s the difference between:
Fish and a fish?
Glass and a glass?
Time and a time?
Ready? Let’s look at the answers:
Fish (uncountable) means the food. You eat
fish.
A fish (countable) means one whole animal,
either living or dead. Compare:
fish in general.
fish.
What about glass and a glass?
Glass is a material. A glass is something
you drink out of. For example:
The sculpture was made of glass.
Would you like a glass of water?
Finally, how about time and a time?
Time is the general meaning of time. It’s
such a basic idea that I can’t really explain
it in more simple terms!
A time has a similar meaning to an occasion
or a period.
Look at some examples:
I don’t have much free time.
How much time will you need to finish this?
There have been many times when I wanted to
give up.
We had a good time at their barbecue.
Can you see the difference now?
So, there are many nouns which can be both
countable and uncountable, often with different
meanings.
There are too many examples to explain them
all here, but I will give you one general
idea which might be helpful.
Often, when a noun can be countable or uncountable,
the uncountable noun has a general or collective
meaning. The countable noun has a specific
meaning.
For example, think about the word hair. It
can be countable or uncountable.
Hair (uncountable) has a general meaning.
It means, for example, the stuff that grows
on your head.
Hair (countable) has a more specific meaning.
Have you ever made the mistake in English
where you say something like:
My friend Jacob has a long hair.
If you say this, you mean that your friend
has one long hair. That’s probably not what
you wanted to say, right?
Instead, say:
My friend Jacob has long hair.
To really understand countable and uncountable
nouns, you’ll have to remember a lot of
information. However, this basic idea can
help you: uncountable nouns are more general
and abstract; countable nouns are more specific.
In this lesson, we’ve talked about countable
nouns, uncountable nouns, and nouns which
can be both.
There are a few strange nouns, which don’t
fit cleanly into any of these categories.
For example, we said at the beginning that
uncountable nouns can’t be plural. You can’t
say rices or knowledges.
That’s generally true, but there are some
uncountable nouns which can only be plural.
They are:
police
clothes
trousers
scissors
You can’t make these nouns singular. You
can’t say one police or one trouser.
Remember to use a plural verb with these nouns.
For example:
The police have interviewed all the witnesses.
These trousers don’t fit well.
Careful with the scissors—they’re sharp.
Another strange word is news. It’s uncountable
and singular, even though it ends with ‘s’.
So, don’t say:
The news are depressing at the moment.
Instead, say:
The news is depressing at the moment.
Finally, there are some collective nouns like
staff, team or crew. Some of these are uncountable
(like staff), and others can be countable,
like team or crew.
These nouns are generally made plural in British
English. In the UK, we say:
The staff aren’t happy with the new uniform.
The team are playing well at the moment.
However, in the US, these collective nouns
are often singular. In the US, you might hear:
The staff isn’t happy with the new uniform.
The team is playing well at the moment.
Both are possible, but try to be consistent.
If you make these nouns plural, then they
should always be plural. If you make them
singular, you should always make them singular.
That said, native speakers aren’t always
consistent. Don’t worry about it too much,
and don’t be surprised if you hear both
forms.
Okay, we have one more thing to do.
The point of uncountable nouns is that you
can’t count them.
But sometimes you need to.
What can you do?
Take an uncountable noun you saw earlier:
rice.
There’s no way to count rice directly. Rice
can never be countable. You can never say
three rices.
But, sometimes you need to count things, even
if they’re uncountable. How can you count
rice?
Actually, there are many ways to do it.
Rice is made up of single grains of rice.
Here is one grain of rice.
You can also have a bag of rice, a packet
of rice, or a portion of rice.
By adding a noun + of, you can make an uncountable
noun countable.
Let’s see how this works in some example
sentences:
There was a single grain of rice left at the
bottom of his bowl.
Can you get two of those big bags of rice?
We’d like three portions of rice, please.
Like with rice, there are often many different
nouns you can add to make an uncountable noun
countable.
That’s the good news. The bad news is that
you need to add different nouns depending
on the uncountable noun you’re using.
Let’s practice this so you can see what
I mean.
Here are five uncountable nouns. How could
you make them countable?
advice
bread
money
furniture
coffee
Think about your answers.
Ready? Let’s look together.
You can give someone a piece of advice, or
two pieces of advice if you’re feeling generous.
Add a piece of to make advice countable.
A piece of is very useful, because you can
use it to make many uncountable nouns countable.
You can also have a piece of bread. With bread
you have other possibilities: a loaf of bread
or a slice of bread.
What about money? You can have a sum of money
or an amount of money. For example, you could
say:
He lost a large amount of money trying to
play the stock market.
For furniture, you could say a piece of furniture
or possibly an item of furniture, although
this is very formal, and not common.
Finally, what about coffee? You can have a
cup of coffee, a packet of coffee, a spoonful
of coffee, or a pot of coffee.
In all of these cases, there are other possible
answers. However, these are the most common
ones.
So, that’s it for this class. Check out
the full version of this lesson on our website:
Oxford Online English dot com. You can read
the text and practise with our quiz.
Thanks for watching and see you next time!