Hi, I'm Niamh and welcome to Oxford Online
English.
In this lesson, you can learn how to answer
one of the questions in Part Two of the FCE
Writing Exam: Writing a review.
For many people, the writing section is the
most challenging part of the FCE test.
In this lesson, you’ll see a step-by-step
process for writing a review.
You’ll see exactly what to do at each stage
and how to improve your FCE writing score.
Let’s look at a sample question:
Book reviews wanted
Have your read a book recently that you couldn’t
put down?
Write a review of the book.
Say why you liked it and who you would recommend
it to.
The best reviews will be published in the
magazine.
There are four steps to writing an effective
answer.
So, what’s the first step?
Read the question and identify exactly what
the examiners want from you.
Your FCE writing is assessed on four points:
First, let’s focus on content.
To get five marks for content you need to
make sure, “all content is relevant and
the reader is fully informed.”
Those aren’t my words—those are the words
from the official mark scheme!
But what do they mean?
Very simple: they mean you need to do everything
the question asks you to do.
Look at our sample question again.
There are three things you need to include
in this task; Do you know what they are?
Number one: you need to write a review of
a book.
This means you should include some basic information
about the book, like its title, the author,
and what genre it is: crime, historical, romance,
etc.
Number two: say why you liked it.
Finally, say who you would recommend it to.
Easy, right?
Yes and no.
It’s simple, but most people don’t get
full marks for content.
You should aim to get five out of five.
Here’s how you do this:
One: make sure you cover everything fully.
Don’t leave any parts of the question out!
Two: make sure you cover everything equally.
In this question, there are three points to
include.
You should have a more-or-less equal number
of words for each point.
Three: make sure you support your ideas with
reasons or details.
Four: don’t include anything unnecessary
or irrelevant.
Your task is to do what the question asks,
and nothing more!
Now, you’ve identified the three things
you need to include.
You can move on to step two: planning!
Planning is the most important step.
The FCE writing test is one hour 20 minutes
long.
Parts one and two are worth equal marks, twenty
each, so you should spend about 40 minutes
on each.
Of those 40 minutes, you should spend five
to ten minutes on planning.
It can be tempting to think, “I need all
of that time to write!
I don’t have time to plan!”
However, this is a bad idea.
Not planning your writing is like going on
a journey without map: you’re likely to
get lost.
Planning is especially important for your
organisation score.
Your writing needs to be well-structured and
coherent to earn marks in this area.
So, when you’re planning, think about questions
like this:
What kind of language should you use: formal,
neutral or informal?
Do you need a title or subheadings?
How should you organise your text?
Do you need an introduction or conclusion?
The answers to these questions will depend
on the exact task.
For a book review, it should probably have
a title, but it doesn’t need sub-headings.
It should be written in a neutral style, and
it should use specific language for the task:
for example to describe books, or make recommendations.
You don’t really need an introduction or
a conclusion, because it’s not an essay;
you’re not trying to prove anything.
Now, let’s make a basic plan together.
When you plan, you need to decide how many
paragraphs you’ll have, and what main idea
will go in each paragraph.
How many paragraphs do you think you’ll
need?
There isn’t one right way to do this, but
you have three main points to include for
your content score.
So, it makes sense to have three paragraphs,
and an extra paragraph to explain what happens
in the book, like this:
Basic information about the book
What happens in the book
Why you liked it
Recommendation
Remember: this isn’t the only possibility.
A different structure might make more sense
for you.
That’s fine; just make sure the structure
is clear in your head.
‘Clear’ means that each paragraph has
one main point, and you know exactly what
that main point is.
After you have your basic outline, you should
add some key words or phrases to each point.
A book I read recently was ‘Breakfast at
Tiffany’s’ by Truman Capote.
Maybe you’ve read it, or perhaps you’ve
seen the film!
So, here’s my plan.
You don’t need full sentences, just an idea
of what you’re going to say.
Pause the video if you want some more time
to read the plan.
Okay, now it’s time to write your answer!
You have between 140 and 190 words.
Count the number of words you write in your
practice answers so you can get a feel for
how much to write.
Ready?
OK.
Here’s our first draft.
Pause the video for as long as you need to
read it.
How does it look to you?
It’s not bad but it’s not perfect either.
Now for the last step!
Try to leave two to three minutes at the end
to check your work.
It can make a difference to your score, so
it’s important!
This is where you can improve your score in
the ‘language’ section of the assessment.
To get a high language score, you need to
“use a range of vocabulary, including less
common vocabulary,” “use a range of simple
and complex grammatical forms,” and make
only “occasional errors.”
Again, these are direct quotes from the Cambridge
mark scheme.
There will be mistakes and things you can
improve in your writing.
Look at our model review again.
There are at least seven things which could
be changed in this answer.
Can you find what they are?
Here are some questions to help you:
Have you forgotten to include anything?
Is all the punctuation, grammar and spelling
correct?
Can you replace very common words with more
interesting, specific vocabulary?
Have you used linking words and phrases to
make it easy for your reader to follow?
Are you within the word count?
These are questions you can ask yourself after
you’ve finished your own practice answers.
Pause the video and read our answer.
See how many things you can find.
First, did you notice I forgot to include
a title?
A book review in a magazine or a newspaper
normally has a title, so our review should
have one, too.
What else could I have done better?
I've underlined a few things in my answer.
Can you improve them?
Okay, let’s see how you did!
First, titles of books and movies are normally
written in italics or placed inside speech
marks.
Let’s put it inside single speech marks
here.
Then, in the 2nd paragraph, 1940s should not
have an apostrophe.
In the third paragraph, I’ve repeated who
lives downstairs which I said in the second
paragraph.
Can you think of another way to say this?
You could say …who rents the apartment downstairs,
…who lives in the apartment below his, or
…who is a tenant in the apartment downstairs.
This shows a greater range of vocabulary and
will improve your language score.
The next one is similar: can you think of
a synonym for more difficult?
How about more challenging?
More difficult is not wrong, but more challenging
is a less common and more specific word.
If you show a range of language, you’ll
get more marks for your language score.
Next, behavior.
Why is this underlined?
Behavior is the American spelling.
It’s fine to use American spelling, but
you must be consistent!
Earlier I spelt travelled with two l’s,
which is British spelling.
I need to change one, so let’s change behaviour
to the UK spelling by adding a ‘u’:
Next, let’s look at the gap at the start
of the last paragraph.
What do you think we could add here?
You could add a linking word or phrase.
It would make it much easier for the reader
to follow.
You would also improve your organisation score.
You have a few options.
For example:
To sum up
Overall
All in all
What about in conclusion?
Would it be a good choice?
Maybe, but it’s not ideal.
It’s too formal!
Save this one for your essay and keep your
review in a neutral style.
Finally, what’s wrong with I’d recommend
it teenagers?
Remember after recommend you need the proposition
to: recommend something to someone.
By correcting these errors and making these
improvements, you could improve your FCE writing
score without very much work.
We used this process to write a review, but
you can use it for any Cambridge writing task,
including the CAE and CPE when you get that
far.
If you enjoyed this lesson and would like
more free lessons, you can visit our website:
Oxford Online English.com.
Good luck with your exam preparations and
let us know when you pass!
Thanks for watching!