Hi, I’m Mikey.
Welcome to Oxford Online English!
In this lesson, you can practice your English
pronunciation with some challenging tongue
twisters.
You’ll see six tongue twisters, and you’ll
hear each one four times.
Each time, you should pause the video and
try to repeat the tongue twister.
Each time you hear a tongue twister, it will
get faster.
Look for the red highlights, which will show
you the pronunciation point which each tongue
twister is testing.
Ready?
Let’s begin!
Both thieving brothers thoughtfully threw
their teeth through the thousandth threshold.
She sees the shiny cheese but she can’t
choose which shoes suit her style.
The four fur shirts were too short for the
walk to work, so I burned them on the lawn
where bored birds are born.
The four fur shirts were too short for the
walk to work, so I burned them on the lawn
where bored birds are born.
The four fur shirts were too short for the
walk to work, so I burned them on the lawn
where bored birds are born.
The four fur shirts were too short for the
walk to work, so I burned them on the lawn
where bored birds are born.
Fewer viewers fail to find waving wives while
veiled whales favour flavoursome wines.
Larry rarely rolls his airy yellow lorry in
really rural rallies.
The sixth stranger asked for extra stamps,
and subsequently my square crisps exploded
onto the straight street.
The sixth stranger asked for extra stamps,
and subsequently my square crisps exploded
onto the straight street.
The sixth stranger asked for extra stamps,
and subsequently my square crisps exploded
onto the straight street.
The sixth stranger asked for extra stamps,
and subsequently my square crisps exploded
onto the straight street.
How did you find that?
Which tongue twister was the most difficult
for you?
Please let us know in the comments!
Check out our website for more free English
lessons: Oxford Online English dot com.
Thanks for watching!
See you next time!