Hi, I’m Marie.
Welcome to Oxford Online English!
In this lesson, you’re going to see nine
strange sentences.
Have you seen the nine sentences yet?
If not, look below the video and read them.
What do you think?
Which ones are correct?
Actually, all nine sentences are correct.
But, we’re sure at least some of these sentences
look weird to you.
In this video, we’ll analyse each of these
sentences, so that you can understand how
they work.
Look at our first three sentences: ‘Have
you ever had to have a tooth extracted?’
‘I would have had to stay longer if I hadn’t
had to go to have my car repaired.’
‘All the medicine he had had had had little
effect.’
What connects these three sentences?
All three sentences play with different ways
to use ‘have’.
‘Have’ can be a main verb which describes
a state, like ‘I have a new computer,’
or which describes an action, like ‘I’m
having lunch right now.’
‘Have’ can also be an auxiliary verb,
which is used in perfect verb forms.
There’s the verb ‘have to’, which you
use to talk about obligations and rules.
Finally, there are some fixed phrases with
‘have’, like ‘have something done’,
which you use when you pay someone else to
do something for you.
For example, you could say, ‘I had my hair
cut yesterday,’ meaning that you paid someone
else to cut your hair.
When you use many of these forms of ‘have’
in one sentence, you can get strange results,
like: ‘Have you ever had to have a tooth
extracted?’
Here, you use ‘have’ in three different
ways.
The first ‘have’ is an auxiliary verb,
because the question is present perfect.
The second ‘have’ is part of the verb
‘have to’, to talk about an obligation.
Finally, the third ‘have’ is part of the
phrase ‘have a tooth extracted’.
What does this mean?
Do you remember?
It means that you’re paying someone else
to do something for you.
Here, it means that you’re paying a dentist
to pull your tooth out; you’re not trying
to do it yourself.
So, can you explain the meaning of the full
sentence?
The question is asking about your past experience,
and whether you’ve ever needed to go to
the dentist’s to have a tooth pulled out.
Does this make sense now?
If not, remember that you can always go back
and review parts of the video which are difficult
for you.
Let’s look at our next sentence: ‘I would
have had to stay longer if I hadn’t had
to go to have my car repaired.’
Can you work out what’s going on here?
Here’s a clue: it’s similar to the last
sentence you saw, but a little more complicated.
The first ‘have’ is an auxiliary.
You use ‘have’ after ‘would’ to show
that you’re talking about the past.
In this case, you’re talking about the imaginary
past: something which didn’t really happen.
Then, you use ‘have to’ to talk about
an obligation.
The third ‘have’, after ‘if’, is another
auxiliary.
Again, you use ‘have’ here to show that
you’re talking about the past, in this case
the imaginary past.
There’s another ‘have to’, again expressing
an obligation.
The final ‘have’ is part of the phrase
‘have my car repaired’, meaning that you’re
paying someone else to repair your car for
you.
Now, you should be able to explain the overall
meaning of the sentence; can you do it?
The sentence means that you needed to take
your car to be repaired, but if you hadn’t
needed to do this, you would have needed to
stay longer at the meeting or event or whatever
you’re talking about.
What about our last sentence?
‘All the medicine he had had had had little
effect.’
This one is a little different.
Can you see what’s happening here?
Two of the ‘hads’ are auxiliary verbs,
and two are main verbs.
This sentence is talking about sometime in
the past, and it says that all of the medicine
he had taken before that time hadn’t worked.
The sentence uses two meanings of ‘have’:
‘have medicine’, meaning to take medicine,
and ‘have an effect’, which is a fixed
collocation, like ‘have a result’ or ‘have
an influence’.
This sentence looks very confusing when it’s
written down, but in speech it hopefully sounds
more logical.
Let's try once more: ‘All the medicine he h/ə/d
had || h/ə/d had little effect.’
The two auxiliary verbs are pronounced weakly,
meaning that the ‘h’ sound either partly
or completely disappears, and the vowel sound
is reduced to a schwa: /ə/.
The main verbs have their full pronunciation,
with /h/ and a full vowel sound: /hæd/.
Also, this sentence is very grammatically
simple; there’s a subject: ‘all the medicine
he had had’, a verb, ‘had had’, and
a complement: ‘little effect’.
You can hear that there’s a short pause
between the subject and the verb.
This helps to make all of the ‘hads’ clear
to your listener.
This is an important point, especially for
your listening: ‘have’ as an auxiliary
verb needs to be reduced and pronounced weakly
in most cases, while ‘have’ in main verbs
keeps its full pronunciation.
And if you’re thinking, ‘pronounced weakly’?
What is he talking about?
Learn about weak forms; there’s at least
one video on our channel which will explain
this to you, and it’s a really useful topic
to study.
Okay, let’s move on and look at our next
group of sentences.
Let’s read the sentences together: ‘The
party was almost over at around ten thirty.’
‘The cat jumped out from behind the sofa.’
‘She gets in in the morning.’
Before we look at these, we want to ask you
a question.
What do prepositions do?
Prepositions can do many things.
They can be used to express time, like ‘It
starts at eight o’clock.’
They can be used to express where something
is; for example, ‘It’s in the cupboard,
on the bottom shelf.’
They can express motion, as in, ‘She walked
towards the lake.’
Prepositions can be used in combination with
nouns, verbs, or adjectives; they can also
be used in phrasal verbs, like ‘get up’.
Finally, prepositions can also function as
adjectives in some cases.
For example, the preposition ‘over’ can
be used to mean ‘finished’.
Like you saw with the different meanings of
‘have’, when you combine all of these
different ways to use prepositions in one
sentence, you can get some strange-looking
results.
Let’s look at our first sentence: ‘The
party was almost over at around ten thirty.’
This sentence contains three prepositions
all together.
What are they all doing?
The first, ‘over’, technically isn’t
a preposition; it’s an adjective which describes
the noun ‘party’, and it means ‘finished’.
Then, you have two prepositions describing
when the party finished: ‘at around ten
thirty’.
The second sentence is similar.
The word ‘out’ is technically an adverb;
it adds information to the verb ‘jumped’;
then, you have two prepositions in a row.
Let’s look: ‘The cat jumped out from behind
the sofa.’
Can you explain what the prepositions are
doing here?
‘Out’—which, remember, is an adverb—goes
with the verb ‘jump’.
The cat jumped out, meaning that the cat wasn’t
visible before it jumped.
Then, the two prepositions describe the movement
and position of the cat.
They tell you where the cat was before it
jumped out: it was behind the sofa.
Overall, the sentence means that the cat was
hidden behind the sofa, and then it jumped
out and you saw it.
Finally, let’s look at our last sentence,
which is possibly the most confusing!
She gets in in the morning.
Can you see what’s happening here?
Although it looks strange to have the word
‘in’ twice in a row, it’s both logical
and quite common in English.
Like the other sentences in this section,
one of the ‘ins’ isn’t actually a preposition.
The first ‘in’ is an adverb, and it’s
part of the phrasal verb ‘get in’, meaning
to arrive.
Then, the second ‘in’ is a preposition
of time: it tells you when she arrives.
So, the meaning of this sentence is: ‘She
arrives in the morning.’
There’s something which connects all of
the sentences you’ve seen.
These sentences can be confusing because the
same word in English can do many different
jobs.
For example, ‘have’ can be a main verb
or an auxiliary verb.
‘In’ can be an adverb or a preposition.
If you understand parts of speech and how
these sentences are constructed, you’ll
see that all of these sentences follow the
rules, even if they look weird!
Next, let’s look at our last group of sentences.
Let’s read the sentences together: ‘That
said, that article that I read argues that
that interpretation is incorrect.'
‘If it’s like that, then that’s it.’
‘There are their bags, over there.’
Again, these sentences are confusing because
the same word, like ‘that’ or ‘there’,
can do more than one job.
Also, in one sentence, you have to deal with
homophones—words which have the same pronunciation,
but a different meaning.
Let’s start with a question: what does ‘that’
mean?
How many ways can you think of to use ‘that’?
First, ‘that’ can be used as a determiner,
like ‘this’ or ‘these’.
You can use ‘that’ to point to one thing
which is distant from you.
You can use ‘that’ as a conjunction, for
example, ‘She told me that I had a nice
voice.’
‘That’ can be a relative pronoun, similar
to ‘who’ or ‘which’.
Finally, ‘that’ is used in many fixed
phrases, like ‘that’s it’, which means
that something is finished.
With this information, can you understand
what’s happening in our sentences?
If not, don’t worry; we’ll look together!
Look at the first sentence: ‘That said,
that article that I read argues that that
interpretation is incorrect.’
First, you have ‘that said’, which is
a linking phrase.
‘That said’ introduces a contrasting idea.
It’s similar to words like ‘however’,
although it’s more colloquial.
The second ‘that’ goes with the word ‘article’.
It means that you referred to this article
before.
The third ‘that’ is a relative pronoun.
It has the same meaning as ‘which’, and
you could also use ‘which’ in this sentence
without changing the meaning.
Then, the fourth ‘that’ is a conjunction
which goes with the verb ‘argue’.
It’s not necessary; you could leave it out
of the sentence and it would still be correct.
Finally, the fifth ‘that’ specifies the
word ‘interpretation’.
Like ‘that article’, this means that you’ve
mentioned this before, and now you’re referring
back to it.
For this sentence, pronunciation is also very
important if you’re reading it aloud.
‘That’ used as a relative pronoun or a
conjunction is often pronounced weakly: /ðət/.
When you use ‘that’ as a determiner, or
in phrases like ‘that said’, it has its
full pronunciation: /ðæt/.
Listen and try to hear the difference: /ðæt/
said, /ðæt/ article /ðət/ I read argues
/ðət/ /ðæt/ interpretation is incorrect.
Using the weak and strong pronunciations correctly
helps your listener to understand the grammatical
structure of the sentence.
What about our second sentence?
Let’s read it together: ‘If it’s like
that, then that’s it.’
This sentence is hard to understand not only
because of the different uses of ‘that’,
but because it has no context.
First, let’s try to understand the end of
the sentence: ‘that’s it’.
Have you seen this phrase before?
Do you know what it means?
‘That’s it’ means something is finished.
For example, imagine you’re ordering some
food in a café.
You order some sandwiches, some muffins, some
coffee, and so on.
The server asks you, “Would you like anything
else?”
You answer, “No thanks; that’s it,”
meaning that you’ve finished your order.
The first ‘that’ in this sentence refers
to something which has been mentioned before,
but without context there’s no way to know
what it means.
Let’s try to give the sentence some context.
Imagine you have a car, and your car breaks
down.
You have to take it to the garage to have
it repaired.
They call you and tell you that the car needs
a new engine, and that the new engine will
cost more than the car is worth.
What would you do in this situation?
Would you pay for the new engine?
Probably not.
You might say, “If it’s like that, then
that’s it,” meaning that if the situation
is like this, then your car is junk, and there’s
no point trying to repair it.
So, this sentence is probably quite pessimistic.
It’s the kind of thing you might say to
admit defeat.
You’re saying, ‘If that’s the way things
are, then there’s no point trying any more.’
What about our last sentence?
This one is slightly different: ‘There are
their bags, over there.’
There are two points to think about here.
First, ‘there’ has more than one meaning.
‘There’ can be used to say that something
exists, as in, ‘There’s a snake in the
toilet!’
‘There’ can also refer to a place which
is distant from you.
Secondly, words can have the same pronunciation
but different spellings and different meanings,
like ‘there’ T-H-E-R-E and ‘their’
T-H-E-I-R.
In this sentence, the first ‘there’ is
used to say that something exists.
The second ‘there’ is used to refer to
a place.
‘Over there’ means a place which you can
see, but which is not close to you.
‘Their bags’ explains who the bags belong
to.
So, this sentence could be an answer to the
question, ‘Where are their bags?’
They’ve lost their bags, and someone wants
to know where they are.
You see them somewhere, so you answer, ‘There
are their bags,’ and then you point to the
bags as you say, ‘over there.’
What about you?
Can you think of any examples of weird sentences
which you find really confusing?
Let us know in the comments!
Thanks for watching!
See you next time!