Hi, I’m Marie.
Welcome to Oxford Online English!
In this lesson, you can learn about a pronunciation
feature which can help you to understand fast
speech and also talk more fluently in English.
What is this pronunciation feature?
It’s called ‘elision’.
Elision is when some words or parts of a word
are not pronounced.
For example, a letter might not be pronounced,
or a syllable might disappear, or sometimes
even whole words are not pronounced fully.
Elision is common in spoken English, especially
in fast, informal speech.
Learning about elision will help your listening
and—if you can use it yourself—help your
speaking, too!
Before we start, don’t forget to visit our
website: Oxford Online English dot com.
You can find all our free English lessons,
including videos and listening lessons.
You can also book online lessons with one
of our many professional English teachers.
But now, let’s look at the first way to
use elision.
In some words, especially words with three
or more syllables, an unstressed syllable
can disappear.
Here’s an example: comfortable.
Comfortable.
Can you hear what’s happening?
The ‘o-r’ after ‘f’ *could* be pronounced
with a schwa sound: com-/fə/-table.
But, it often isn’t pronounced at all.
You link directly from the ‘f’ to the
‘t’: comfortable.
Try it after me: comfortable.
Let’s do one more example together: restaurant.
Restaurant.
Can you hear which syllable is missing?
The ‘a-u’ is often not pronounced,
so you can link directly from the ‘t’ to the ‘r’: restaurant
Look at five more words.
In each of these words, one syllable is often
not pronounced.
Can you see which syllable can disappear?
Pause the video if you want more time to think.
Ready?
Let’s look together.
In ‘history’, the ‘o’ is often not
pronounced: history.
History.
In ‘temperature’, the second ‘e’,
after the ‘p’, is often not pronounced.
So, you can link from the ‘p’ to the ‘r’:
temperature.
In ‘vegetable’, the second ‘e’ can
disappear: vegetable.
Vegetable.
In ‘chocolate’, the second ‘o’ is
not generally pronounced: chocolate.
Chocolate.
Finally, in ‘different’, the first ‘e’
almost always disappears, so you link directly
from ‘f’ to ‘r’: different.
Different.
How did you do?
Could you find the disappearing syllables?
Can you pronounce the words with the elision?
Go back and repeat this section if you want
more practice.
At this point, you probably have some questions,
like “Is there any way to know which words
have disappearing syllables?”
And, “Do I need to speak like this all the
time?”
The first question has a simple answer: basically,
no.
However, there aren’t that many words where
this happens.
If you practise the pronunciation of the words
in this section, that’s a good start.
The second question is more important.
With all elision, there isn’t one ‘correct’
way to say something.
Also, different speakers pronounce things
in different ways.
So, you might hear some people pronounce ‘comfortable’
with a direct link from the ‘f’ to the
‘t’, or you might hear some people pronounce
a short schwa sound in between: comf-/ə/-table.
However, if you pronounce a long vowel sound
here, it will sound strange: com-/fɔː/-table.
That doesn’t sound right.
In summary, there’s a range of possible
pronunciations.
You don’t have to pronounce things in one
specific way, but you should try to get your
pronunciation inside that range.
Next, let’s look at another useful form
of elision.
In some cases, consonant sounds are changed
or not pronounced.
This is especially true for /t/ and /d/ sounds
at the end of a word.
For example, look at this phrase:
last summer.
Can you hear what happens to the ‘t’ at
the end of ‘last?’
Listen once more: last summer.
There are two possibilities here.
The ‘t’ can disappear completely, so that
you link the ‘s’ in ‘last’ and the
first ‘s’ of ‘summer’ together: ‘las_summer’.
Or, the ‘t’ can become glottal.
This means the ‘t’ is half pronounced.
Think about it like this: when you say /t/,
you do two things.
First, you put your tongue behind your top
teeth, and build up pressure in your throat.
Then, you move your tongue down and back,
and release the air pressure to make the sound:
/t/.
When you pronounce a glottal ‘t’, you
just do the first part.
You put your tongue in position and build
up pressure as if you’re going to say /t/,
but then you never release the sound.
See if you can hear it: ‘last summer’.
‘Last summer’.
This is common with ‘t’ sounds at the
end of words.
Also, there’s a rule: if one word ends in
a consonant plus ‘t’, and the next word
starts with a consonant, then the ‘t’
either disappears or becomes glottal.
The same is true for /d/ sounds.
For example: ‘red banana’.
/d/ and /t/ are similar sounds; you make the
same movement with your tongue for both.
So, they behave in a similar way.
Here, in the phrase ‘red banana’, you
might drop the ‘d’ completely: ‘reb_banana’.
Or, you might pronounce a glottal consonant,
where you put your tongue into position to
make a /d/ sound, but you never release it:
‘red banana’.
Let’s practise with some phrases.
First question: which final ‘t’ and ‘d’
sounds can disappear?
Remember that this rule applies only if a
word ends in a consonant plus ‘t’ or ‘d’,
*and* the next word starts with a consonant.
And when we say ‘disappear’, we don’t
necessarily mean that the sound is not pronounced
at all.
It might disappear completely, or it might
be pronounced with a glottal consonant.
What about ‘I didn’t look at it?’
There are three words ending in ‘t’ here.
The ‘t’ in ‘didn’t’ can disappear,
but the other two need to be pronounced: ‘I
didn_look at it.’
In, ‘Just say what you think’, the ‘t’
in ‘just’ can disappear.
The ‘t’ in ‘what’ might disappear
in fast or informal speech: ‘Jus_say what
you think.’
In ‘stand next to the window’, the ‘d’
in ‘stand’ can disappear.
The ‘t’ in ‘next’ is linked to the
‘t’ in ‘to’: ‘Stand next_to the
window.’
In the last phrase, the ‘d’ on ‘hold’
will disappear: ‘Can you hold my bag for
a second?’
Let’s read the phrases together one more
time.
Try to repeat them:
I didn’t look at it.
Just say what you think.
Stand next to the window.
Can you hold my bag for a second?
Like we mentioned before, there’s a range
of possible pronunciations here.
There isn’t just one correct way to say
these.
However, it does sound strange to pronounce
a full consonant sound.
This can add a vowel sound, which sounds unnatural.
For example, if you say ‘last-/ə/-summer’,
this doesn’t sound so good.
You’ve seen how elision works with syllables
and sounds, but elision can also apply to
whole words.
Let’s see how!
Look at a short sentence: I’m not ready.
Now, listen again: ‘m’not ready’
What happened?
Can you hear?
Listen one more time: ‘m’not ready’.
When speaking fast, you can often shorten
or remove pronouns like ‘I’, ‘you’,
or ‘he’ from the start of a sentence or
question.
You can do the same with auxiliary verbs like
‘am’, ‘has’, ‘is’ and so on.
Let’s look at one more example: ‘He’s
left already.’
Can you hear what I said?
Listen again: ‘He’s left already.’
Here, the word ‘he’ is shortened or removed,
so the sentence starts with a *very* short
‘i’ vowel linking to a /z/ sound: ‘iz’left
already’.
Let’s do some more practice!
We’ll read five sentences.
You’ll hear each sentence twice.
Try to write them down.
Pause the video between sentences if you need
time to write.
Ready?
Let’s start!
You did it!
It’s upstairs.
Do you live near near?
Has he paid you back yet?
Have you tried it?
Listen once more:
You did it!
It’s upstairs.
Do you live near here?
Has he paid you back yet?
Have you tried it?
Do you have five sentences written down?
Let’s check!
Did you get them right?
Let’s see what’s happening here.
‘You’ can be shortened to /jə/, with
a schwa sound.
This schwa can be so short that it’s difficult
to hear: y’did it!
In ‘it’s upstairs’, ‘it’s’ can
be shortened to a /ts/ sound: ts’upstairs.
‘Do you’ can be shortened to /djə/.
Again, the vowel sound can become *very* short:
dya live near here?
‘H’ sounds at the start of a word often
disappear.
So, ‘has he’ can become /əzi/, again
with a very short schwa in many cases: /əzi/
paid you back yet?
Similarly, ‘have you’ can be shortened
to /vjə/, as in /vjə/ tried it?
Like with everything in this lesson, you don’t
need to pronounce everything exactly in this
way.
But, it is useful to understand how sounds,
syllables and words can be shortened or removed.
Understanding these ideas will help you to
understand natural speech in English.
There’s a lot of information in this topic,
and we could have given many more examples,
but this lesson’s long enough already.
What about you—can you think of any other
examples where sounds, syllables or words
disappear?
Share your examples in the comments!
Thanks for watching!
See you next time!