Hi, I’m Oli.
Welcome to Oxford Online English!
In this lesson, you can learn how to do parts
three and four of the Cambridge B1 Preliminary
speaking exam.
Before we start, one question: do you find
it difficult to understand spoken English?
Yes?
Help yourself and turn on the subtitles now.
All our videos have English subtitles; click
the CC button in the bottom right of your
video player to turn them on.
If you’re watching on a mobile phone, use
the settings icon at the top.
In part three of the B1 preliminary speaking
test you talk to your partner, not to the
examiner.
It lasts two to three minutes.
At the beginning, the examiner will say: “Now,
in this part of the test you’re going to
talk about something together for about two
minutes.
I’m going to describe a situation to you.”
Then, the examiner will give you a booklet
with the task.
You’ll see several pictures.
It might look something like this.
Then, you’ll hear the instructions.
For example: “A family wants to go on a
trip this weekend.
Talk together about the different places the
family could visit and decide which trip the
family would most enjoy.
All right?
Now, talk together.”
Listen to the examiner carefully, because
the instructions won’t be written on the
task.
If anything is not clear, ask the examiner
to repeat the instructions.
First point: remember that the situation is
about other people, not about you.
This task is not asking you to describe where
*you* want to visit this weekend.
It is asking you to talk about where the *family
in the picture* should visit.
Don’t say ‘I think the castle is a good
idea because I love history.’
This trip is not for you.
You are only recommending ideas for the family.
Instead, say ‘I think the castle is a good
idea because it would be educational for the
family.’
Now let’s look at another situation.
Pause the video if you want more time to read
and think.
Remember also that the instructions will not
be written on the task in your real B1 speaking
exam!
Let’s look at how to begin.
Do you know how you should start?
A good way to start is to ask your partner
a question.
For example, for this task, you could ask
‘Which present do you think is the best?’
Or, ‘What do you think about getting him
a camera?’
Let’s look at another task.
Imagine you’re in the B1 speaking test.
This is your task.
Can you think of a question you could ask
your partner to start?
Pause the video and try to make one or two
questions you could use to start this task.
Do it now!
Could you do it?
Of course, there are many possibilities!
You could ask ‘What do you think about bringing
a camera?’
Or ‘Do you think they should bring a guidebook?’
Asking a question is a good way to start.
What next?
The conversation should be fifty per cent
you speaking and fifty per cent your partner
speaking.
You don’t get extra points for speaking
more.
Give your opinion about something, and then
ask your partner a question.
Your opinions on each idea should not be very
long – one or two sentences maximum – then
ask another question.
Ask your partner to respond to your ideas.
Let’s go back to our first example.
Remember: one or two sentences, then ask a
question.
For example: ‘I think going to the beach
is a good idea if the weather is nice because
the children could play in the sea.
What do you think about the family going to
the beach?’
Let’s move on to our next point: linking
your ideas when you speak.
In part three of the B1 speaking exam, you
need to link your ideas with comparisons and
contrasts.
Look at our second task again.
Imagine you’re in the exam.
Your partner says ‘I think the mobile phone
is a good idea because our classmate could
keep in contact with us.
What do you think about the camera?’
And then you reply ‘I don’t think the
camera is a good idea because cameras are
old-fashioned.
What do you think about the book?’
These are good answers and ideas, but as a
conversation, it sounds unnatural.
There’s no connection between one answer
and the other.
Here’s a better example.
Your partner says ‘I think the mobile phone
is a good idea because our classmate could
keep in contact with us.
What do you think about the camera?’
You reply ‘I don’t think the camera is
a good idea, because today all mobile phones
have cameras.
What do you think about the book?’
This sounds better, right?
Comparing and linking your ideas helps you
to sound more like you’re having a normal
discussion.
Our next point: you need to react to your
partner’s ideas and suggestions.
How can you do that?
When your partner speaks, you need to listen
actively.
Don’t just sit there like a robot.
React, nod your head, or say something to
show how you feel.
If you agree with what your partner says,
you could say something like: ‘I agree’,
‘good idea’, ‘that’s interesting’,
‘you’re right’, ‘that’s true’
or ‘I think so too’.
If you disagree with your partner, remember
to be polite.
You could say ‘really?’
‘I’m not sure about that’, ‘I don’t
think I agree’, ‘I don’t think so’
or ‘good idea, but I prefer…’
Also, when you disagree with your partner,
give a reason, or an alternative suggestion.
For example: if your partner says, ‘I think
the book is a good idea because books are
not that expensive’, and you disagree, you
could reply ‘I don’t think I agree.
I understand that a book would be a cheap
present, but we want to get our classmate
something special to remember us, like the
watch.’
When you’ve finished discussing your options,
you should make a decision together.
At the end, ask your partner something like
‘what have we decided?’ or ‘shall we
choose one?’
Remember: you don’t have to be honest.
If your partner thinks that one idea is better,
you can agree just to finish the conversation.
It doesn’t matter if you really agree or
not.
If your partner is unsure, try to lead the
decision.
Look at our first task.
You could say, ‘I think the family should
go to the beach, because we agreed it has
a lot of activities for all of the family.’
This shows that you have control over the
conversation.
What about our second task?
You could say, ‘I think we can agree that
the mobile phone is the best idea because
our classmate can keep in contact with us.’
Again, you’re controlling the discussion,
but also involving your partner.
Doing these things can help your score.
Make sure you leave enough time to reach a
final decision together, but you also need
to talk for the full two to three minutes.
If you stop too early, the examiner will not
say anything, and you will be sitting in uncomfortable
silence.
When preparing for the B1 speaking exam, try
to get a feeling for how long you need to
speak.
Don’t answer the question too quickly.
After around two and a half minutes, start
trying to reach a final decision.
Now, you should understand how to do part
three of the B1 Preliminary speaking exam.
What about part four?
In part four, the examiner will ask you questions,
and you’ll discuss the questions with your
partner.
This means you need to speak to both the examiner
and your partner in part four.
The questions will be on a similar topic to
part three.
Part four lasts around three minutes.
For example, if the topic in part three was
connected to travel, you might hear questions
like: ‘Do you prefer to travel with friends
or alone?’
‘What can people learn from travelling to
different countries?’
‘What do you like doing when you go on holiday?’
Think: how could you answer these questions?
Here’s a sample answer for the first question:
‘I prefer to travel with friends.
It’s more interesting.’
What do you think?
Good answer?
It’s not terrible, but it could be better.
This answer is just two short sentences, and
it doesn’t have many ideas.
First, try to join your ideas together using
words like ‘but’, ‘although’ or ‘because’.
For example: ‘I prefer to travel with friends,
because it’s more interesting.’
Next, try to use more specific vocabulary.
‘Interesting’ is very general.
For example: ‘I prefer to travel with friends,
because it’s more sociable.’
Then, try to add more ideas to your answer,
like this: ‘I prefer to travel with friends,
because it’s more sociable, plus you always
have people to talk to and hang out with.’
Remember these three points: join your ideas
together, use specific vocabulary, and add
ideas to your answer.
In this way, you can make your answers stronger!
Like in part three, you should ask your partner
for their opinions.
The examiner will ask questions in part four.
However, you should also talk to your partner.
So, at the end of your answer, you can ask
your partner a question like ‘How about
you?’ or ‘Do you agree?’
Also, react to what your partner says.
For example, imagine your partner says ‘People
can learn a lot from travelling to different
countries.
For example, they can see how things like
culture, food and architecture are different
around the world.’
How could you react to this?
First of all, you could agree or disagree.
For example, you could say, ‘Yes, I think
so, too’ or ‘I’m not sure I agree with
you.’
Even better, try to add your own ideas.
For example: ‘Yes, I think so, too.
Also, people can learn about different traditions,
for example how festivals are celebrated.’
Or, ‘I’m not sure I agree with you.
Travelling is a great experience, but I think
you can learn about other countries’ culture,
food and so on even if you don’t go there.’
Let’s try another one.
Imagine that your partner says: ‘When I’m
on holiday, I just like lying on the beach
and doing nothing all day.’
How could you respond to this?
Try to make two or three sentences.
Say if you have the same opinion, or not,
and add your own ideas.
Pause the video and say your response aloud.
Could you do it?
There are many possible answers.
Let’s look at two.
You could say ‘I’m the same way.
My work’s really busy, so when I’m on
holiday, I just want to relax and forget about
the stress of daily life.’
Or, you could say ‘I guess I’m quite different
to you.
I love active holidays, so I enjoy things
like hiking, rafting, cycling, and so on.
If I stayed on the beach all day, I’d get
really bored.’
In general, in part four, try to add reasons,
details and examples to your answers.
This will let you use a wider range of grammar
and vocabulary, which improves your score!
Let’s put these ideas together.
For each question the examiner asks, you should
do one of two things.
First, you can give your answer, then ask
your partner for their opinion.
You can also continue the discussion by reacting
to what your partner says.
Or, you can let your partner speak, and then
react to what they say.
A good idea would be to take turns, so that
you answer one question first, and then your
partner speaks first for the next question.
It’s better in part four if you and your
partner can control the discussion, rather
than waiting for the examiner to speak.
The examiner might stop you if you speak for
too long or go off-topic, but that’s not
a problem.
That’s it.
Good luck if you have a B1 Preliminary speaking
exam soon!
Thanks for watching!
See you next time!