Hi, I’m Marie.
Welcome to Oxford Online English!
In this lesson you can learn how to talk about
football in English.
Do you play football?
Do you watch football, or support a team?
You can learn useful language to talk about
who you support, talk about a football match,
and more!
Before we start, check out our website: Oxford
Online English dot com.
Are you watching on YouTube?
Look in the video description for links.
You can find the full version of this lesson,
which includes the script for you to read,
and a quiz so you can test your vocabulary
skills!
You can also book online lessons with one
of our professional teachers, in case you
need more help with your English.
Our teachers can help you with spoken English,
writing, pronunciation, IELTS preparation,
or whatever else you need.
Oxford Online English dot com.
One more thing: don’t forget to turn on
the subtitles if you need them!
All our videos have English subtitles, and
many have subtitles in other languages, too.
Click the ‘CC’ button in the bottom right
now.
OK, let’s talk about football!
You’re a Villa fan, right?
Villa?
No!
Spurs.
I’m Tottenham through and through.
Oh, really?
I like Spurs.
They’ve done well recently.
They’ve been top four for the last few seasons,
right?
Yeah, they’re always there or thereabouts,
but it’d be nice to actually turn that into
some trophies one day.
We haven’t won anything major for a long
time.
Who do you support?
Newcastle.
My Dad’s from there, and he took me to games
when I was younger, so I’ve stuck with them.
I’m not a fanatic, but I try to go to at
least a couple of games a year, although it’s
not much fun at the moment.
They’ve got a good side though, no?
Yeah, it’s not that.
The owners won’t invest, so they’ve been
underperforming for the last few years.
It’s frustrating.
What do you think for this year?
You think City will win it again?
Probably, though I think Liverpool have a
shot, too.
How do you think Spurs will do?
Well, I’d be happy enough with 4th, and
very happy with 3rd.
We need to be more consistent, though.
Last year we dropped too many points in easy
games.
What about Newcastle?
Realistically, if we finish in the top half
of the table it’ll be a good season.
I just hope we don’t get relegated again…
Are you a football fan?
Who do you support?
You could answer this by saying ‘I support
…’, as in ‘I support Manchester United,’
or ‘I support Barcelona.’
Or, you could just give the club name.
In the English Premier League, club names
are often shortened.
Look at five short names for Premier League
clubs.
Do you know which clubs they are?
Did you know?
Here are the answers.
If you say ‘City’ or ‘United’ when
talking about English football, most people
will understand ‘Manchester City’ and
‘Manchester United’.
There are many clubs which have ‘City’
or ‘United’ in their name, but these are
historically two of the biggest.
Anyway, what about your club?
Look at three questions.
Think about how you could answer these questions.
Before you do, let’s see some language from
the dialogue which might help.
Look at the highlighted words and phrases.
Do you remember how they were used?
Could you explain what they mean?
‘Through and through’ means that you give
100% to your club.
If you say ‘I’m Tottenham through and
through’, you mean you are—and always
have been—a big Tottenham fan.
A ‘fanatic’ in this context means a very
enthusiastic fan.
If you say ‘I’m not a fanatic’, you
mean that you support your team, but maybe
it’s not a big part of your life.
‘There or thereabouts’ means ‘near the
top, but not the best’.
If your team is there or thereabouts, you
mean that they’re close to the top teams,
but not one of the best in the country.
Maybe you finish 3rd, 4th or 5th every year.
If your team underperforms, it gets worse
results than you would expect.
Maybe you have many great players, but you
don’t win as often as you should.
Top teams need to be *consistent*.
This means they play at a high level every
week.
The opposite is inconsistent.
Inconsistent teams might play well one week,
and badly the next.
Finally, if your team gets relegated, they
finish in one of the bottom places in the
league, and so they drop down to the league
below.
Getting relegated is one of the worst things
that can happen to a team!
So now, what about your team?
Look at the questions you saw before.
Think about how you could answer them.
Maybe you could use some of the language you
just saw.
Pause the video, think about your answers,
and practise saying them out loud.
OK?
Could you do it?
If it’s difficult, remember that you can
go back and watch the dialogue and explanations
again.
Next, imagine that you just watched an exciting
match.
How could you talk about it?
Let’s see!
Wow!
What a game!
Yeah, real end-to-end stuff.
5-5?
How often do you see a 10-goal draw?
I thought West Brom were out of it, but they
kept coming back.
To be 5-2 down against a team like United,
and score three…
They never stopped fighting.
On the one hand, it’s disappointing that
we blew a three-goal lead, but it was such
a great match that I can’t be too unhappy.
In the end, I think a draw was the right result.
Obviously I’d have loved West Brom to win,
but neither team deserved to lose.
True, though your lot were so bad in the first
half.
I don’t know what happened at half time,
but you looked like a completely different
side after the interval.
Yeah, I know what you mean.
I think United sat back a bit too much in
the second half, too.
Maybe they thought they had won it in the
first half.
Yeah, we didn’t look as sharp in the second
half.
Here’s a question: what’s the best football
match you can remember?
At the start of the dialogue, you heard the
phrase ‘end-to-end stuff.’
You can use this to describe a match which
was fast-going and full of action.
Look at some more phrases from the dialogue,
but with some words missing.
Can you remember the missing words?
Remember that you can go back and listen to
the dialogue again if you want.
Are you ready?
Let’s see the answers.
Can you explain what these phrases mean?
‘Out of it’ means that you don’t have
a chance.
If a team is three goals down, normally you
can say they’re out of it, because most
teams don’t win from that position.
You can also use ‘in’ with the opposite
meaning.
For example ‘They may be a goal down, but
they’re still in the game.’
This means that even though they’re losing,
they still have a chance to win.
If a team recovers from a losing position
and gets a draw or a win, then they come back.
‘Come back’ can be a verb or a noun.
Look at two examples.
‘Blow a three-goal lead’ means to lose
a winning position.
‘We blew a three-goal lead’ means we were
three goals ahead, but then the other team
came back to win or draw.
In general, if you say ‘you blew it’,
it means ‘you failed’.
It’s conversational.
‘Your lot’ means ‘the team you support.’
It’s also conversational, but it’s quite
common among UK football fans.
If a team sits back, they don’t try to attack,
and maybe they don’t give 100%.
Sometimes, teams sit back when they’re already
winning, because they don’t think they need
more goals.
Another conversational expression which is
popular recently is ‘park the bus’, which
has a similar meaning.
If a team parks the bus, they defend deep,
and don’t move players forwards.
Saying that a team parks the bus is usually
a criticism, because it describes a style
of play which is often boring to watch, even
if it’s effective sometimes.
Finally, if your team looks sharp, they are
playing well and moving fast.
‘Sharp’ means something like ‘focused’
or ‘dangerous’.
You want your team to look sharp, especially
if they have a big match, like a cup final.
Has your team ever played in a cup final,
or won any trophies?
Let’s see how you can talk about that next.
Big night for you on Thursday, right?
The Europa Final?
Yeah, I’m looking forward to it.
You think you’ll win?
Could do.
I think both teams are quite evenly matched.
In a knockout competition, you’ve always
got a chance.
We’ll see!
It’d be a big deal though, wouldn’t it?
First European trophy?
Yeah, that’d be nice.
Plus, it gets us into the Champions League
next year.
That would be a first, too.
Didn’t you win the FA cup a couple of years
ago?
No, we got to the final, but then we lost
in extra time.
We haven’t won anything in recent years
except the League Cup, and even that was five
years ago.
I think I remember that match.
Didn’t you win on penalties?
Yeah, it was a long shootout.
It went to 10-9 or 9-8 or something crazy.
Well, a win’s a win!
Generally, football teams take part in two
kinds of competition: leagues, like the Premier
League, La Liga or Serie A, and cup competitions.
Cup competitions can be domestic or international.
English football has two cup competitions:
the League Cup and the FA Cup.
The FA Cup is generally considered more prestigious.
Other European leagues mostly have one domestic
cup, but a few countries have two.
Then, you have international cups.
In Europe, the most famous is the Champions
League.
The Europa League is the second-tier cup.
Cups are knockout competitions, meaning that
in most cases, if you lose one match, you’re
out.
Some cups have a league phase, like the group
stage of the Champions League, or the World
Cup.
In a knockout match, what happens if it’s
a draw?
The match might go to extra time.
If that doesn’t produce a result, then you
have a penalty shootout.
Look at two sentences:
Notice that you win or lose *in* extra time,
but *on* penalties.
Now, let’s practise!
Look at three questions.
Can you answer these questions?
Like before, pause the video and make your
answers.
Read them out loud, write them down, or do
both!
Let’s look at one more thing: talking about
players and transfers.
You looking forward to the new season?
Yeah, of course, though I’m less optimistic
than I could have been.
We didn’t have much luck in the transfer
window.
You still have a good team, though.
Sure, but we’ve lost some players.
Kanté’s gone, Schwarzer’s gone, and I
don’t think Riyad Mahrez will stay for long.
Plus, with injuries, we needed at least one
centre back, a holding midfielder, a winger,
and probably more.
But you still have Vardy.
He’s still a top striker.
Yeah, no doubt.
He’s getting on, though.
He might have one or two more good seasons
in him, but we need to think about replacing
him, too.
Well, count your blessings.
We have a transfer ban, and our keeper’s
injured, so we might not even have a recognised
goalie for our first match.
You have so much depth in your squad, though.
I think you’ll be OK.
Here’s a question: how many football positions
can you name in English?
How many did you get?
In general, you have a goalkeeper, defenders,
midfielders and forwards.
In each group, you have more specific words.
For example, defenders can be centre-backs,
left-backs, or right-backs, and there are
other positions, too.
Midfielders can be classified by both where
they play and their role.
A ‘role’ can be defensive or attacking.
For example, a holding midfielder is a defensive
midfielder who plays in the centre.
A winger is usually an attacking midfielder
who plays on the left or the right side.
There are many other possible midfield positions,
depending on the team’s tactics.
Forwards can be strikers, whose job is to
score.
Some teams might play a second forward behind
the main striker, or wide forwards, who play
on either side of the main striker.
What about your team?
Who’s the best defender, midfielder and
forward?
Which players would you like to see in your
team?
Let’s see some more phrases from the dialogue
you can use to talk about players and transfers.
Can you explain what these mean?
‘Top’ means ‘one of the best’.
‘Getting on’ means ‘getting older’.
It’s conversational.
Of course, getting older is relative here;
footballers, especially forwards, often start
getting slower after 30, and few are
playing at a high level after 35.
A transfer ban is when a club is not allowed
to buy new players.
If a club breaks the rules around transfers,
they might get a transfer ban for a few months.
Recently in the Premier League, Chelsea were
given a 12-month transfer ban for breaking
the rules on approaching players aged under
18.
Finally, sentence four means that the club
has more than 11 good players.
If your club has a deep squad, it means that
injuries or losing one or two players won’t
be a problem, because there are other good
players to take over.
What about you?
Who do you support, and who are your favourite
players right now?
Share your opinions in the comments!
Thanks for watching!
See you next time!